<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The certaine and true newes, from all the parts of Germany and Poland to this present 29. of October, 1621. Published by authoritie.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08153</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.35C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119029</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854236</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854236</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19645</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08153)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19645)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1100:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The certaine and true newes, from all the parts of Germany and Poland to this present 29. of October, 1621. Published by authoritie.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by F. K[ingston] for B. D[ownes] and are to bee sold by William Lee, at his shop in Fleetstreet, at the golden Bucke, neere Serieants Inne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 11788.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 11788 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19645:1"/>
            <p>THE CERTAINE AND TRVE NEWES, FROM ALL <hi>THE PARTS OF</hi> GERMANY AND POLAND, <hi>TO THIS PRESENT</hi> 29. <hi>of October,</hi> 1621.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authoritie.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by F. K. for B. D. and are to bee ſold by <hi>William Lee,</hi> at his Shop in Fleetſtreet, <hi>at the golden Buck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, neere Serieants Inne.</hi> 1621.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19645:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19645:2"/>
            <head>From Hungary, Octob. <hi>28. 1621.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N <hi>Hungary,</hi> affaires goe not very well for <hi>Bethelem Gabor,</hi> and the Marqueſſe of <hi>Iagen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorff,</hi> are already in <hi>Morauia,</hi> and make themſelues Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the field, winning one place after another with great ſpeedineſſe: yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe the treaty of <hi>Niclausburgh</hi> goeth forward.</p>
            <p>The accord betweene the Duke of <hi>Bauaria</hi> and Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> is broken off, wherefore the Duke of <hi>Bauaria</hi> followeth him foot by foot.</p>
            <p>They in <hi>Franckendale</hi> behaue themſelues very braue and manfully, and if other places had done the like, it would not haue beene in the <hi>Palatinate</hi> as it is.</p>
            <p>Euen now, I haue newes, that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> is ariued at a place called <hi>Necker,</hi> within foure miles of <hi>Heydelberg:</hi> and it is thought that <hi>Franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endale</hi> will bee aided or ſuccoured by him, next Munday or Tueſday.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Newenmarik,</hi> the Ieſuites and Capuchines preach openly in the Caſtle, and Pariſh Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19645:3"/>
               <hi>From Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtaw in Sileſia, the</hi> 17 <hi>of Octob.</hi> 1621.</p>
            <p>Although the purpoſed Diet in <hi>Sileſia</hi> vvas de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred by the Lords and States of the Countrey: yet is it appointed againe by the Emperour and Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> that it ſhall be kept, and begin ere October be finiſhed, becauſe all manner of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration belonging thereunto is in a readineſſe, and already ſet forward.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſſe of <hi>Iagendorff</hi> was in <hi>Sileſia</hi> with 20000. taking one place after another, and ſo went into <hi>Morauia</hi> to the Prince of <hi>Tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiluania,</hi> to whom came 10000. of <hi>Walachia,</hi> who ſpoile and burne all they meet withall, ſo that it is reported, that theſe forces together, are very neere 50000. I meane <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelem Gabors,</hi> and the Marqueſſe of <hi>Iagendorff.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Glaty</hi> is not as yet taken, but holds out ſtill.</p>
            <p>Out of <hi>Poland,</hi> newes is come, that there were ſlaine in the laſt conflict betweene them and the <hi>Turkes,</hi> 20000. <hi>Polonians,</hi> and at leaſt 40000. <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is alſo certaine, that the Marqueſſe of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg</hi> ariued in the end of September laſt, at <hi>Warſchan</hi> in <hi>Poland,</hi> whom the King of <hi>Poland</hi> met, with 500. <hi>Heiduckens,</hi> and many horſemen, and ſo the ſaid Marqueſſe very ſhortly after receiued the feoud of the King.</p>
            <p>Out of <hi>Pruſsia</hi> the newes is, that the King of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> hath taken in <hi>Riga,</hi> or <hi>Rigwe,</hi> and that the King of <hi>Poland</hi> is gone for certaine, as reſolued to meete with the <hi>Turkes</hi> armie.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Sileſia,</hi> it is likely it will be very dangerous to liue and continue, and therefore many of them are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19645:3"/>
about to buy land in the Country of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> fearing it will fall out very ill with them in their owne Countrey.</p>
            <p>The Lord of <hi>Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> is come vnto <hi>Iagendorff,</hi> with 3. Companies of foot, and 4. peeces of Artillery, and ſo put a Garriſon the rein, from whence he went vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Trappaw,</hi> and tooke with him the Ordnance that were in <hi>Iagendorff,</hi> getting a great bootie by the way.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Morauia</hi> there is like to be an vprore, and the <hi>Wallachiens</hi> will fall directly to the Marqueſſe, wherupon they ſuſpect the Marqueſſe in the vpper <hi>Sileſia,</hi> who would march thorow their Countrey with 8000. <hi>Hungars</hi> and 6000. <hi>Dutch,</hi> which hath cauſed a great feare amongſt the Souldiers on all ſides.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From Vienna,</hi> 25. <hi>Octob.</hi> 1621.</p>
            <p>After that Captaine <hi>Reuber,</hi> contrary to his oath, had ſurrendered vp the Towne of <hi>Scalitz, Bethelem Gabor</hi> went forward with his forces all along <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauia,</hi> and as ſoone as the Souldiers which lay in <hi>Strafnitz</hi> perceiued his comming, they made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues maſters ouer their Captaines and Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, hurting and wounding ſome of them, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally one of <hi>Haugenitz</hi> very ſore, becauſe he would not yeeld vnto them, and afterwards they threw him out at a window.</p>
            <p>Thus when they had bound all their Captaines and Commanders, they deliuered them and the Caſtle vp vnto <hi>Bethelem Gabor,</hi> who would haue put them all to the ſword; but by the meanes of the Marqueſſe of <hi>Iagendorff</hi> they were ſaued: yet a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19645:4"/>
great feare was raiſed in the Countrey by this meanes, that the treaty of <hi>Niclaus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urgh</hi> ſhould haue beene deferred: but ſince there ariued 9000. <hi>Sileſians</hi> in <hi>Morauia,</hi> it is begun.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, the <hi>Hungarians</hi> did ſet vpon <hi>Holl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſchaw,</hi> the Lord Cantilar of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the Lord Generall, with their followers, and tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from them what they had: notwithſtanding, the Earle of <hi>Emerid, Titzio,</hi> and fiue other <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Lords are come vnto the Treatie, and ſhall (no queſtion) haue what the whole country can afford.</p>
            <p>Three dayes agoe there was put in priſon heere, an <hi>Italian,</hi> called <hi>Cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>la,</hi> with his ſonne and ſeruants, for coyning certaine pieces of money, amounting to the value of a thouſand pound.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bethelem Gabor</hi> and the Marqueſſe of <hi>Iagendorff,</hi> haue taken in moſt places on this ſide the Marſh, and our forces haue likewiſe taken in the beſt quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters on the other ſide all along, till you come to <hi>Randiſch,</hi> where they meane to remaine on both ſides, vntill a Treaty of peace is concluded.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lean</hi> forces doe daily great hurt, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing burning and ſpoiling the Countrey heerea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Newſtadt:</hi> and although the chiefe places are beſet with Souldiers, as <hi>Hanbach, Prugg, Alten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, Eiſenſtad,</hi> and <hi>Newſtadt,</hi> yet they dare not venter vpon the enemy, either for feare of diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiture, or leauing their Townes naked.</p>
            <p>Since our forces left the <hi>Schutt</hi> and <hi>Thombia,</hi> and went into <hi>Morauia,</hi> they haue indured great ſcarci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſtill want neceſſary prouiſion: for the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers liuing by prouant, and getting none, could
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19645:4"/>
neither paſſe thorow, nor trauell any longer, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that many horſes died for want of prouen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and as many Souldiers for want of victuals, ſo that they are not able to reſiſt the enemy: beſides, the ſickneſſe &amp; dearth which is increaſed amongſt them, doth trouble &amp; affright them more &amp; more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Out of Prage,</hi> 27. <hi>of Octob.</hi> 1621.</p>
            <p>They in <hi>Tabor</hi> doe hitherto hold out, and haue only 50. very expert in ſhooting, ſo that none dare ſhew themſelues before it: all the forces which are heereabouts, were brought together, being about 4000. foot, and 600. horſe, who ſhould haue giuen an aſſault vpon the Towne, but finding themſelues too weake, they deſiſted: whereupon they determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to vndermine it: wherein likewiſe they failed, by reaſon of the ſituation vpon a ſtony and hard ground.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Lichtenſtein</hi> cannot as yet goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with his regiment of foot, and 500. horſe, becauſe all the men which can be muſtered, are brought before <hi>Tabor.</hi> Likewiſe the Dukes forces goe not forward, but lye heere and there on the high wayes ſide, robbing and ſtealing from all they meet: and although the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> hath beene called vpon diuers times by the Emperor to march with his Army into <hi>Morauia:</hi> yet for any thing we heare, he is not ſo much as a going.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Hungarians</hi> all this while are falne very ſtrong into <hi>Morauia,</hi> doing very much hurt, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the <hi>Imperials</hi> follow them, to intercept their outrage, yet are they too weake to doe any good vpon them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19645:5"/>The Prince of <hi>Lichtenſtein</hi> went yeſterday in the forenoone with a few toward <hi>Rundis,</hi> where the Arch-duke <hi>Charles</hi> is to meet him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From Neurenbergh, Octob.</hi> 26. 1621.</p>
            <p>On Sunday laſt, there paſſed by vs <hi>Monſieur Tilly</hi> with 66. companies of foot, 44. troopes of horſe, 9. Peeces of Ordnance, 1500. waines, and 5000. horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, all which went preſently to <hi>Furth,</hi> where they pitched their Campe and reſolued to remaine.</p>
            <p>Hitherto they haue had prouiſion ſent vnto them from hence; they did much hurt by the way, and terrified all the Countrey: Whether he followed with this Army after the Count of <hi>Mansfield,</hi> who then lay at <hi>Rottenbergh,</hi> is vncertaine, becauſe they ſuddenly incamped, as (belike) vnderſtanding of a new Treaty betweene the Duke of <hi>Bauaria</hi> and the Count <hi>Mansfield.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>From the Palatinate, the</hi> 26. <hi>of Octob.</hi> 1621.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Ritterſchaft</hi> lieth as yet at <hi>Neckerhanſen,</hi> and thereabouts.</p>
            <p>The enemy before <hi>Franckendale,</hi> hath got the halfe moone by <hi>Raldenlech</hi> already, and they haue beene vpon the wall at <hi>Franckendale,</hi> but were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to a retreat by the valour of the defendants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they looke daily for Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> who as it is thought, will quarter himſelfe about <hi>Masbach,</hi> and then no doubt, as ſoone as he comes, <hi>Franckendale</hi> will be aided and releeued.</p>
            <p>Laſt Friday there was a skirmiſh betwixt the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and Captaine <hi>Obertrant,</hi> who carried away with him three Peeces of Ordnance, leauing the fourth in the lurch: all theſe he took from them very brauely.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19645:5"/>At <hi>Manhaime</hi> the enemy would haue taken the Ship-bridge avvay, but they vvere beaten backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vvith no ſmall loſſe.</p>
            <p>Laſt Saterday the enemy made another ſtrong aſſault vpon the Sconce before <hi>Franckendale,</hi> vvherein the <hi>Engliſh</hi> lay, but vvere beaten off a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vvith the loſſe of 700. men, vvhereof ſome of them ſtucke ſo faſt in the mariſh, that they vvere there cut in pieces. There is a rumor that the Earle of <hi>Nederyſenburgh</hi> vvas ſlaine vvith a Peece of Ordnance: ſome ſay he vvas but hurt: but it is ſure, that certaine chiefe Captaines vvere ſlaine in that aſſault. About midnight they made another aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault vpon the halfe Moone, and tooke it vvith tvvo Peeces of Ordnance, tvvo tunne of povvder, vvith certaine clothes: but ere they could goe quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, all was recouered, and they loſt againe many men, beſides 300. that were wounded. There were found dead of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſome 80. but it is vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine how many they brought into the Towne with them. Their hope is now in Count <hi>Mansfield:</hi> for they haue ſent the enemy word, they haue nothing for them but powder and ſhot: in which, they were as good as their words, as it ſhould ſeeme: for newes came preſently againe, that they haue beaten the <hi>Spaniards</hi> once more from the wall of <hi>Franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>From the Palatinate, the</hi> 30. <hi>of October.</hi> 1621.</p>
            <p>That the Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> marching day and night, is come into the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> his forces being 16000. hath ioyned himſelfe with Sir <hi>Horacio Vere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:19645:6"/>
               <hi>Spinola</hi> hearing of it, made toward them with his forces: they perceiuing him willing to fight, ioyned battell with him, ſlaying 3000. of his men; and following him ſo long as day-light laſted, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led many of them in the flight.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19645:6"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
